[SQUEAKING]
[RUSTLING]
[CLICKING]
ERIK DEMAINE: All right,
welcome to the grand finale
of dynamic programming in 6.006.
4 of 4.
Today we are going to focus in
on a particular type of problem
that we saw at
the very beginning
with Fibonacci, which is when
you have an integer input,
and a natural thing to do
with that integer input
is look at smaller
versions of that integer.
And this is going to lead
us to a new notion called
pseudopolynomial time.
We've talked a lot in this
class about polynomial time
being a good running
time, but pseudopolynomial
is a pretty good running time,
and we'll talk about that.
And it relates to
these integers.
We'll only look at
two new examples--
rod cutting and subset sum--
but then we're going to
review all the examples we've
seen from a kind of
diagonal perspective.
So as usual, we're applying our
SRTBOT framework, subproblems,
relations, topological order,
based cases, original problem,
and time.
Quick review-- so the
hardest part is getting
the right set of subproblems.
And there's some
natural choices.
For sequences, we try
prefixes, suffixes, substrings.
For integers, like in Fibonacci,
there's a given number,
and we want to compute that
at the n-th Fibonacci number.
What we ended up doing
was solving Fibonacci
numbers for all input numbers--
input integers between
0 and that number n--
or in this case, capital K.
And that's a general technique,
and we'll see two more
examples of that today.
Otherwise, we take
products of these.
And often, that's
enough, but sometimes we
need to add more subproblems
in what we called subproblem
expansion, often with
extra constraints that
let us remember some
state about the past.
My canonical example of
that is the piano fingering,
where we had to remember what
our fingering assignment was,
in some sense, from the previous
step in order to compute
the transition cost.
And this is a very
powerful technique.
You can also use it to play
Super Mario Brothers optimally.
If you have a
constant size screen
and all you need to remember
is what's in the constant size
screen, if everything
outside that screen resets,
you can just add that state as
a parameter to your subproblem
and you'll be able to solve
Super Mario Brothers--
anyway very useful.
And that was the
focus of last lecture.
We won't talk about
it much here today.
And then we relate these
subproblems recursively,
and this is basically the test
of whether your subproblem
definition was correct is, can
you write down a recurrence
relation--
which is just a
recursive algorithm?
And there's a nice
general procedure
for how to come up with
these relations, which
is to just think up some
question about the subproblem
solution that, if
you knew the answer,
reduced to smaller subproblems.
And then you just locally
brute force all the answers
to that question,
which I like to think
of as guessing the
answer correctly,
and then just directly
calling the recursive things.
But then, at the
end, you have to pay
for that guess by looping over
all possible guesses in order
to guarantee that you
actually find the right one.
So once you identify this
question, it's very easy.
DP is all about just brute
force anything that you want.
And usually that leads to
pretty good running time,
as long as the number
of possible answers
to that question is polynomial.
Then we need to check
this relation is acyclic,
and then it's--
often reduces to
finding a path--
like a shortest path or
something-- in a DAG--
a subproblem DAG.
We need some base cases.
We need to make
sure we can solve
the original problem using
one or more subproblems,
and then we analyze
the running time
as usually a number
of subproblems
times the amount of
non-recursive work
in the relation plus
however much time it took us
to solve the original problem.
So that was our framework.
We've seen it four times now,
slightly refined each time.
We've mostly added
some general techniques
for subproblem definition
and how to write relations.
So let's do a new example,
which is rod cutting.
This will be pretty
straightforward,
but it will serve as a
contrast to the next example
we talk about, subset sum.
So what is the problem?
The name rod cutting
comes from the book CLRS,
but it's actually a
pretty practical problem--
maybe not for cutting rods.
But you could imagine you
have some resource of a given
length.
Because I have been wood--
hardwood shelf shopping
recently, I like to think,
if you have a big
plank of hardwood
and you get some price
for selling that length,
but you could also
cut that plank
into multiple pieces of
various lengths that sum to L.
And you could sell
them individually,
and maybe you make
more money that way.
And that's what this
problem is all about.
So you're given the value
of every possible length
you could cut.
We're going to assume all
lengths have to be integers,
scaled so that that's true.
So capital L here is
the original length,
little L is a candidate length
of a piece you might cut,
and v of l is the value for
cutting off a length L rod--
sub-rod.
And we're going to
assume, when we cut,
we don't lose any material.
You could probably
adjust for that,
but it's not
terribly interesting.
And we want to know, what
is the best way to split up
our big rod of length capital
L into various rods of small L
length--
potentially different lengths?
So I'll call this the
maximum value partition.
In mathematics, this is called
partition, a bunch of numbers
that sum to a given number.
And we want to maximize
the total value, naturally.
So here's an example.
Let's say our
original length is 7
and we have this table for
lengths 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7--
all the different lengths.
I'm going to write
down a value that's
an integer for cutting off a rod
of that length and selling it.
It's like the sell price.
It's presumably monotonic,
but doesn't have to be.
Maybe people really
like buying powers
of 2 length or something,
and so those sell higher.
So this doesn't have to be
monotonic, but in this example,
it is.
And so I have this
rod of length 7,
and I could sell it
directly for $32,
let's say, but I could
also split it into, say,
a length 1 rod and a
length 6, or a length 1
rod and two length 3's, or
length 3 and a 4-- anything
that sums to 7.
And probably the
most natural thing
to do for this problem
is a heuristic.
This would be a greedy--
bang for a buck heuristic
is what is usually called--
it's to take the ratio--
how much money do I
get for a given length?
Divide v of L by L, and
try to maximize that.
If I had to pick a single item
and sell many of that type
that, would be the
optimal thing to do.
So this has a ratio of 1.
That's bad.
This has a ratio of 5.
That's better.
And you stare at
it long enough--
I believe 6 is the best--
has the highest ratio,
slightly more than--
I can't divide--
slightly better than--
let's see.
AUDIENCE: Slightly
worse than 4--
ERIK DEMAINE: Slightly
was 4 the best?
Slightly worse than 4?
What do you mean?
AUDIENCE: 31 over 6 is
slightly less than 4?
ERIK DEMAINE: Oh, slightly--
I see.
The ratio is
slightly less than 4.
Thank you.
Yeah-- which, all of these
others are somewhat worse.
If I double the 3 value, I
get 26, which is quite a bit
less than 31.
The closest competitor,
I think, is 2,
because if you multiply
this by 3, you get 30.
So if I sold three
2's, I get $30,
but if I sell one 6 which--
is the same quantity--
I get $31, a slight improvement.
And so this item maximizes
bang for buck, for that ratio.
And so one natural
partition is 6 plus 1.
I sell one out of length 6, and
that leaves a lot of length 1.
And this will give
me $31 for the 6,
and $1, which gives me $32.
But this turns out to
not be the best, which
is actually the same as if
you just sold it outright.
But in fact, you can
do better by selling--
this is not obvious--
stare at it for a while--
a 3 and a 4--
also sums to 7.
Then we get 13 plus 18,
which is hopefully bigger--
33.
Nope, I did not get it right.
That's too small.
We're going to take these
two and sell 3 plus 2 plus 2,
and I get 13 plus 10 plus 10.
Remember, 2 was a close
competitor for the ratio for 6,
so it's a little
better to sell 2's--
two 2's and then a 3,
because then we get $33.
And that turns out to be
the best for this problem.
And it seems really
tricky to figure this out.
In general, there
are exponentially
many different partitions--
can't afford to try them all.
Question?
AUDIENCE: Can I have
negative values?
ERIK DEMAINE: Can I have
negative values in here?
I think that will work fine.
I'm not allowed to have
negative lengths or 0 lengths.
I don't want 0 lengths to
actually give you something,
because then I'd just
cut infinitely many 0's.
But the v of L, I think,
could be negative.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Do I have
to use a whole bar?
ERIK DEMAINE: Do I have
In this problem, yes.
I think it wouldn't
change much, if you didn't
have to use the whole bar.
We can think about those
after we write the DP.
So let's solve this with SRTBOT.
So what's the input
to this problem?
I didn't mention this
is an integer length--
positive integer length.
So we have one input,
which is an integer L,
and we have another
input, which is--
I guess it's an
array of integers.
So this is a sequence
and this is an integer.
So if we look at our
list of nice subproblems,
we could try prefixes, or
suffixes, or substrings
of the value
structure, or we could
try, for that integer,
smaller integers.
That's actually what I prefer.
I think the way to think about
this is to jump ahead to,
what do we want to--
what feature of the solution
do we want to guess?
And presumably, we
should think about,
what is some length of rod
that we will cut and sell?
So I have this big rod.
Maybe I sell the whole thing.
Maybe I cut off a thing
of size 1 and sell it.
a size 2 and sell it.
But I have to sell
something, unless I'm not
selling anything.
There's only L different choices
for what rod lengths to cut off
first, and so we can just brute
force that in order L time.
So what problem do
we get if we cut off
an integer of some
small L length?
Well, we just get
the same problem
with a rod of length
capital L minus small L.
The values don't change.
It happens that I won't use
the big values, if I cut off
some amount of
the problem, but I
like to think of this as
we're just-- all we're doing
is decreasing big L.
And so my subproblems are
going to be, for each small L,
less than or equal to big
L, solve that problem.
So x of L is max value partition
of length L-- little L--
for little L equals
0, 1, up to big L--
so just the same problem,
but with different choices
for big L. So this is using
this integer subproblem.
Now, in this
example that happens
to correspond to
prefixes of the v array--
because, if I only have
length up to little L,
then I really only
need the prefix
of the value array
up to little L.
So you could think
of it that way.
That's also fine.
But I think this way's a
little more generalizable.
OK.
So I claim this is a
good set of subproblems,
because I can write a recurrence
relation, which is actually
pretty simple.
Like I said, we want
to choose some piece--
so we're given a lot
of length little L.
I want to choose
how much of that
rod to sell in the next piece.
So I could cut off
something off length 1,
or I could sell the
whole thing, or cut off
any piece size in between.
And the money I
will get for that
is whatever the
value of that piece
is plus, recursively,
the maximum I can get
from all the remaining pieces--
sorry-- from the
remaining length,
which is little L minus p--
so very simple inside the
formula-- just the value
for the first piece.
We're guessing, what
is the first piece
we'll cut off and sell?
We get the value for
that piece, and then
recursively, we
see what's the best
we can do with the remainder.
Now, we don't know what size
the first piece should be,
so we just brute force it.
We try all possible
choices for p
and take the max that we
get out of this formula
over that choice.
And that's guaranteed to
find the best overall,
because we must
cut off some piece.
Now, if you wanted to
allow not selling anything,
in the case of
negative numbers, you
could just add a 0 to
this max, and then you
might stop early if
there's nothing left that's
worth selling.
OK, topological order,
it is very simple.
We just have these capital
L different problems,
and if you look at--
oh.
Yeah.
So we're looking at L minus
p. p is always at least 1,
so we're always
strictly decreasing
L in this recursive call.
And so as long as I
solve the problems
in order of increasing
little L, I'll
guarantee that, whenever
I'm solving x of little L,
I'll have already solved all
the things I need to call.
So if you're writing
a bottom-up DP,
this would just be for loop
L equals 0 up to big L,
in that order.
This is equivalent
to the statement.
But the key is to check
that this is acyclic,
because we're always
referring to smaller L,
and so increasing L is a
valid topological order
in this subproblem DAG
defined here, where there's
an edge from an earlier thing
to evaluate to a later thing
to evaluate.
OK, base case would be x of 0.
That's the first thing
we want to compute here.
And indeed, this formula
doesn't make much sense
if I have x of 0, because
I can't choose a number
p between 1 and 0,
even non-strictly,
and so what does it mean?
Well, if I have a
rod of length 0,
I can't get any money out of
it, so that's it-- just 0.
That's an assumption, but
a reasonable assumption.
You don't get
something for nothing.
OK, then we have the
original problem,
which is just the length L rod.
And then the time to
compute this thing--
how many subproblems are there?
Capital L plus 1-- so we'll
say theta L subproblems.
And we'll multiply by the amount
of time to evaluate this max--
just a constant number
of things in here,
not counting the recursive call.
And so it was spent--
takes little L time.
Little L is certainly,
at most, big L,
and so we'll say
big O of big L time.
It's actually a
triangular number,
but it will only affect
things by a constant factor.
So we get L squared
time, and we're done--
so very simple,
straightforward DP.
At this point, we've seen
much more complicated examples
than this.
But it highlights
a question, which
is, is theta L squared
polynomial time?
So is this a reasonable
running time?
And I claim the
answer is yes, this
is a reasonable
polynomial running time.
You might say, well, of
course, it's a polynomial.
Look, this is a polynomial--
L squared.
That's a quadratic polynomial.
But it's a quadratic polynomial
in L. And we haven't really
thought about this too
hard, but what does it
mean to be polynomial time?
And this is a notion that's
properly called strongly
polynomial time.
We won't worry about
that strongly too much
in this class, but if
you look this up online,
you'll see the difference.
Polynomial time means
that the running time
is polynomial in the
size of the input.
And the size of the
input is, for our model,
measured in words--
machine words.
Remember, our good old
word RAM, W bit words.
It's been very
useful, because it
lets us assume things
like adding two numbers
is constant time, as long as
these numbers fit in a word,
as long as they're
at most W bits.
And generally, we
assume all the things
we're manipulating fit
and a machine word,
because that's what-- the
case where we normally work.
And so the natural way to
measure the size of an input--
so in this example, in
this problem, rod cutting,
the input is a single number L,
and this value array, v of L,
which is capital L numbers--
integers.
Doesn't mention
integer value here.
Throughout this class, we
assume that all the integers,
unless otherwise
specified, fit in a word.
So we've got one word
here and L words here,
so the total size of the
input to this problem
is L plus 1 integers.
So in this problem,
input size is
L plus 1, which we can think
of as just L. It's theta L.
So I explicitly didn't want
to use n in this problem,
because usually we use the
letter n for the problem--
not quite always.
But input size always
means input size,
and so here, we can compute it
in terms of the specification--
involves L plus 1 word inputs.
And so polynomial time should be
polynomial in that input size--
in L plus 1, in our example.
So of course, L squared is
polynomial and L plus 1--
so good.
Yes.
OK, the next example
I'm going to show
is going to be very similar,
but the answer will be no--
make it more interesting.
But it'll still seem
pretty reasonable.
So we'll come back to
that issue in a moment.
Let me first show you
what the subproblem DP
looks like for this problem--
again, took me a while to
draw, so please admire.
So this is the same
example of these values--
1, 10, 13, 18, 20, 31, 32--
drawn here on a graph.
It's the complete graph
oriented in this increasing way.
I think this is called a
tournament in graph theory.
So we have the base
case over here.
This corresponds to a length
0 rod, where we get no money.
And over here we have our
full right of length 7,
and claim the best
we can do is 33.
And what's happening here
is, for every value like 3--
I could sell a rod
of length 3 for $13--
there's an edge that goes from
each vertex to one 3 higher,
and those all have a
weight of 13 on them.
And then what we're
essentially trying to do
is find a longest path
from here to here--
longest because we want to
maximize the sum of values
that we get.
And we know, if we negate
all the weights, that's
the shortest path problem,
so we could solve that
with shortest paths in a DAG.
But I've drawn here the shortest
path tree from the base case.
So it actually tells us that,
if we had a rod of length 7,
the best thing to do is to
sell it directly for 31.
The bold lines here are
the shortest path tree--
or the longest
path tree, I guess.
And if we had something like
10, we should sell it directly.
If we have something
of length 20,
we should sell one thing of
length 2 and another thing
of length-- sorry--
one thing of length 4.
Then we should sell one
thing of length of 2,
and one of length 2, and
we get 2 times 10 points.
And for the 33 case, we
sell one thing of length 2,
one thing of length 2, and
then one thing of length 3
is optimal.
So you can read lots of
information from this.
And if you write
down the DP code,
this is effectively what it's
computing, from left to right.
OK, let's move on
to a second problem
today, which is subset sum.
So here we are given
the same multiset.
Multiset means that
I can repeat numbers.
So this is just a
sequence of numbers.
But I'd like to
use set notation,
because I want to use subsets,
because it's subset sum.
So this is n integers.
And we're also given a target
sum, and we want to know,
does any subset sum
to the target sum?
This is actually a similar
problem to rod cutting,
because rod cutting-- we also
had to split up our number
L into different values
that seemed to capital L.
So capital T here is playing
the role of capital L.
But before we were allowed
to cut into any lengths,
and so it was easy.
In particular, L
sums to L. Here,
presumably, T is not
in this multiset,
and we need to find a
combination of numbers here
that add up exactly to T.
Sometimes that's possible.
Sometimes it's not.
We're only allowed to use each
number once, or as many times
as it appears in the subset.
OK, so here's an example.
Say A equals 2, 5, 7, 8, 9.
And two examples are
T equals 21 and T
equals 25 for that same set.
So can I get 21 out of these--
this involves arithmetic.
That's hard.
Let's see.
If I add 7 and 8, I get 15--
not quite what I want.
I'm going to cheat,
look at my answer.
Yeah-- close.
I see-- 5, 7, 9.
So this is a yes answer
to the question--
does there exist any subset--
because 5, 7, and 9
sum to exactly 21.
And T equals 25--
I don't know a good way to
prove to you that there's no way
to write 25 with
these numbers, other
than I wrote a program
to try to all subsets
and-- or you could write
a program that runs the DP
that we're about to give.
And it will output no.
There's no succinct
way, as far as we
know, to prove to someone that
the answer's no for a given
target sum.
There is a nice, succinct
way to prove the is yes.
I just give you a subset--
we'll talk more about
that next lecture.
But these are some examples
of the question you might ask,
and the answer that
we're looking for.
This is what we call
a decision problem.
In its original form,
we're just interested
in a yes or no answer.
It's a single bit.
Of course, in the yes
case, we might actually
want to find the
set, and we can do
that as usual with
parent pointers,
just like in the
bold lines over here.
We'll get to that in a moment.
Most of the problems we've been
seeing with dynamic programming
are optimization
problems, and we're
trying to minimize or
maximize something,
and so we always put a max on
the outside in the relation.
Here we're going to
have to do something
that involves boolean values--
yes or no, true or false.
OK, so let's solve it.
This is actually also going
to be pretty straightforward,
in that we can just use our
standard sets of subproblems.
So just like the
previous problem,
we have, on the one hand,
a sequence of integers,
and on the other hand, we're
given a single integer T.
And what turns
out to be right is
to use prefixes or suffixes
on this sequence and integers
less than or equal to T.
Let's think about why.
So that was SRTBOT
for rod cutting.
This is SRTBOT for subset sum.
Again, I'll look for--
look ahead to, what feature of
the solution should I guess?
Well, I have these n numbers.
Each of them could be
in my subset or not.
So I have this binary choice.
For each AI is it in S or not?
That's a lot of
questions to answer.
I can't answer them
answer them all at once,
but I could just start with
the first one and say, well,
is a0 in S?
Yes or no?
There's two answers--
locally brute force.
If I do that, what
happens to my problem?
What new subproblems
do I run into?
What do I want to recurse on?
Well, I've eliminated a0.
That will leave a
suffix of the AIs.
So suffixes on capital
A seem like a good idea.
And what about my target sum?
Well, it depends.
If I put a0 in my set
S, then the target sum
for the remainder is T minus a0.
So T went down, and so
I need in my subproblems
to represent smaller
target sums also.
So this is how you
figure out what
subproblems you should use.
You could just try
prefixes on this, suffixes
on this, substrings on this.
And yes or no-- do I include
smaller versions of T here?
But you can also
just think about--
trying to write a recurrence
relation first, see
what things you were
naturally recursing on,
and then formulate the
subproblems that way.
So that's what I like to do.
So I'm going to have a
subproblem for each suffix.
So that's x of i.
And for each target sum-- and
I use these capital letters
for the actual
target sum so that I
can use lowercase letters
for smaller versions of them.
So this is going to
be, does any subset--
remember, don't-- first, most
important thing is to define
what your subproblems are.
Don't just say, it's the
same problem, but where
I replace blah with blah.
It can be very ambiguous.
Does any subset S of the
suffix A from i onwards
sum to little t?
And we're going to
have this subproblem.
The other important
thing is to say
how many subproblems
there are and what
your indices can vary over.
So i is going to
be between 0 and n,
and t is going to be
between 0 and big T. OK.
So remember, subproblems
is n plus 1 times 2 plus 1,
or theta n times T. Cool.
Now I claim I can write a
relation, like I said, by--
so we have this suffix from A--
from I onwards in A, and
so I'm just going to--
because I'm looking at suffixes,
I want to keep with suffixes.
So I should try to guess
what happens to A of i,
because then what will remain
is A of i plus 1 onwards.
And A of i can either
be in my subset
S or not, so
there's two choices.
So x of IT is going to be--
involve two things.
So there's an operator
here, and then I
have a set of two
items, which is--
I could choose to not
put A of i in my subset.
In that case, I've eliminated
A of i, and what remains
is A of i plus 1 onwards.
And I didn't change
my target sum.
I haven't put anything
in S, so I still
want to achieve the same sum.
So this is the case
where AI is not an S.
And then the other
case is I put A of i
in S. In that case, again,
I've eliminated A of i,
and so what remains
to figure out
is what happens to A
of i plus 1 onwards.
But now my target
sum is different,
because I put a
number in my set.
And so among these items, they
should sum up to not little t
anymore, but now little t
minus what I just added--
which is AI.
So then, if, in
this subproblem, I
get something that
sums to t minus AI,
and then I add AI to that
set, I will get something
that sums to exactly
T. And so that's
a valid solution
to this problem.
And because we have brute
forced all possibilities--
there were only two--
if we combine these
in the suitable way,
then we will have
considered all options.
Now, what do we want here?
Normally I'd right max or min,
but this is a decision problem.
The output is just yes or no.
So this is a yes or no answer.
This is a yes or no answer.
And so what I want is or.
In Python, this
would be called any--
just, are any of
these things true?
Because if there's any way to
construct a set that sums to T,
then the answer to this is yes--
cool-- so very simple, actually.
This is one of the
simplest reoccurrences.
But we're solving what I think
is a really impressive problem.
We're asking, is
there any subset?
There are exactly 2 to
the n subsets of A here.
And we're, in some sense,
considering all 2 to the n
of them, but because
we split it up
into n local choices that
are binary, and do them
only one at a time--
this is the local brute
force versus global versus.
Global brute force
would be trial subsets,
sum them, see which ones add up.
But we're, in some
sense, collapsing
a lot of these choices
and reusing subproblems.
That's the whole point
of dynamic programming.
For the rest of the sequence,
from i plus 1 onwards,
I don't really care exactly
which subset you choose.
I only care what it sums to.
And that collapses a
lot of different options
into the same thing.
I really just want to
know, is there any way
to do it with exactly this sum?
If I said, give me all of the
different subsets that sum
to T that would be
exponential time,
but because I'm just asking a
yes or no question, this choice
only takes constant time, and
we get to some them, instead of
product them--
because we're using memoization.
That is the beauty of
dynamic programming and the--
this time analysis
rule that we only
have to sum over subproblems
because we only compute
each subproblem at once.
Without memoization, this
would take exponential time,
just like Fibonacci.
With memoization, magic.
I just think it's beautiful.
So even though it's
one of our simpler DPs,
I think it's an impressive one.
OK.
Topological order-- well, let's
look at these function calls.
So here we have to be
a little bit careful.
When we call x recursively,
we always increment i.
But sometimes we
don't decrement t.
Sometimes t doesn't go down.
So if I wrote
decreasing t here, that
would be bad,
because sometimes I
call with the same value of t,
and I don't want to get into--
I want to ensure that this
has already been computed
when I try to compute this.
So i is the right thing, and
we should say decreasing i.
It doesn't actually matter
how we order with respect
to t just any order
that is decreasing--
i will be good, because
these function calls always
increase i.
OK, we need a base case.
Let's see.
Given this aspect, I
think the natural thing
is to have a base case
when my suffix is empty,
which is when i equals n.
So this is x of n, t--
for any little t, because we
don't have a lot of control
how t is changing.
But this is easy.
So this is saying,
if I give numbers,
what sums can you represent?
The only sum I can
represent is 0.
So if t equals 0, then
the answer is yes.
And otherwise, the answer is no.
So that's my base case,
and that's enough.
And we needed this base case,
because if we wrote x of n, t,
this would try to
call x of n plus 1,
which doesn't make sense.
But x of n colon is a
natural suffix, which--
we only allowed i to go up to
n, and that's the empty suffix.
So this is enough.
We need the original
problem, which
is the entire string
from 0 onwards,
and capital T for little t.
That's our target sum.
And then the running time--
as I said, there are n
times t subproblems--
theta.
And the amount of work we
spend for each one that
isn't recursion is constant.
We just do a couple
subtractions, additions,
do an or and recursive
calls-- so constant time.
So n times t is the running
time of this algorithm.
Let me show you an example
as a subproblem DAG.
These are hard to draw,
but they're easy to read.
I think they're
helpful to show what's
really going on in this DP.
Remember, every node
here corresponds
to a possible
subproblem we can have.
So we have the choices for
little t on the top, choices
for little i on the left.
So the original problem we
care about is i equals 0,
T equals 6.
This is the same example
that I showed you before,
where we have 2-- or no,
it's a different example.
Sorry.
My new set a is 3, 4, 3, 1--
four numbers here.
My target value is 6.
This is definitely possible.
I can add 3 and 3.
This shows that a doesn't
have to be sorted.
We're not assuming anything
about the order of a,
and we're allowed
duplicate values.
And we see indeed, there's a y
here for yes, it is possible.
And how did I compute that?
Well, I just drew
a bunch of arrows.
So there's vertical arrows here,
always going from each problem
to the next one above
it, because we have--
this dependency xi of t
calls x of i plus 1, t.
The calls are going
in this direction,
so the dependency
order is you have
to compute things lower down
before you compute things up
here.
And indeed, down here
is the base case,
where we right yes for
the first problem and no
for all the others, because
we don't have any numbers.
We can't represent
anything above 0.
And then we have
these blue lines.
I just drew them a different
color so they stand out--
hopefully.
And they correspond
to the numbers here.
So our first choice is, do
we include a0 which is 3?
So that's only possible if we're
trying to represent a number
that's greater than or equal
to 3-- which reminds me,
I forgot to write down--
in this DP, I need to say this
option is only an option if AI
is less than or equal to T.
Just move my comments here.
Those are the same.
So this notation means I
put this item in this set
that we take an order of
only if this condition holds.
Otherwise, I omit it,
because it's not a choice.
Why is that important?
Because I don't want to call
x on a negative value of t.
We only are allowed to call
x here, when t is between 0
and capital T. So that's
subtlety, but important
for a correct DP.
That's why there's no edge
from here, for example,
that goes through 3 to
the left, because there's
no vertex there.
There's no subproblem.
So only for little
t, from 3 onwards,
we have this edge
that goes 3 back,
and that's just the same
pattern over and over.
Then our next number is 4,
and so we have these edges
that are-- go 4 to the right.
Then our next number's
3, so we can have
edges that go 3 to the right.
And then our next
number is 1, so we
have these nice diagonal
edges that go 1 to the right.
And then what's happening
in here at each stage--
let's take an interesting
one-- maybe this vertex--
is we look at each of
the incoming neighbors
and we take the or.
So the incoming
neighbor here has a no.
Incoming neighbor
here has a yes.
And so we write
a yes here, which
means that, given just
these numbers, 3 and 1,
we can represent the number 3--
namely, by taking
this edge of 3--
sorry-- of length 3 and
then just going straight
down to a base case.
That's yes.
That's representing 0.
So in this case, we--
this example-- I didn't draw
the parent pointers here,
but they're in the notes--
this yes is possible--
not from going this way,
but from going this way.
So we take the number 3.
Then we go down, which
means we skip the number 4.
And then we go left, which
means we take the number 3.
And then we go which means
we skip the number 1.
So we can represent
6 as 3 plus 3--
cool.
So subset sum-- not only can
we solve the decision problem,
but by following parent
pointers in the yes instances,
we can actually
find a valid subset.
Question--
AUDIENCE: You added that
condition to the relation?
ERIK DEMAINE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Is it possible
to deal with that
by spending your
number of base cases?
ERIK DEMAINE: Good question--
it's a generally
useful technique
to add if conditions to the
cases to only when they apply.
You can write a lot
of DPs that way,
and that's why I
wanted to stress it.
You could, instead of
adding this condition,
allow the case that
little t is negative.
But you have to think about,
how negative would it be?
You might say, well, maybe
t between minus big T
and plus big T is enough,
but I don't think so.
It should be we're at some
value t and we subtract some AI.
We don't know how the AIs
compare it to big T. Probably
they're less than
or equal to big T,
because they're not useful
if they're bigger than big T.
So you could first prune the AIs
to guarantee all the AIs less
than big T. Then minus
big T to big T would work.
Otherwise, it's minus the
maximum AI up to big T
would be enough, I think.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Does this restrict
to only positive integers
in the input?
ERIK DEMAINE: I am
implicitly assuming here
that all the AIs are positive.
I think you can solve it
with negative numbers,
but it's not--
AUDIENCE: Maybe do
it in recitation?
ERIK DEMAINE: Maybe we'll
do it in recitation.
It's not a trivial
change to this DP.
I've definitely thought
about it before.
Yeah, so I should have said
positive integers here--
cool.
All right, so that's subset sum.
But we come back to
this question of,
is this a good algorithm?
Is it polynomial time?
So we have this running
time, n times t.
So a new question is, is
n times big T polynomial?
And the answer is no.
Why?
Because for this problem,
what is the input size?
How many words of
input do I have?
Well, I have these
n integers, and then
I also have the target sum.
So similar to up above,
our input sizes n plus 1.
But now the labels
really matter.
Before it was L plus 1,
and a running time was
a function of L. Now our
input size is just n plus 1,
but our running time is a
function of both N and T.
Not polynomial in
input size n plus 1.
You cannot write that n times
capital T is less than or equal
to n plus 1 to the 27th power,
because you just don't know how
N and T relate.
Maybe T is, at most,
N Then we're happy.
But maybe it's not.
Maybe T is 2 to the N. Why
could it be 2 to the N?
Because what do we
know about capital T?
We assume implicitly
throughout the course
the T fits in a word.
That means it's a W bit number.
So that means it's,
at most, 2 to the w.
And you might think, well, we
know about a relation between w
and n.
So we know T is, at most,
2 to the W, if it's W bits.
And we know that our
assumption is always
that w is at least log n.
That's the word RAM trans
dichotomous assumption.
But notice, we
don't know anything
about an upper bound on w.
In order to upper
bound T in terms of n,
I'd need to say that
w is at most log n.
Then this would be at
most n, and we'd be done.
But that's not very interesting.
And generally, we allow w to be
arbitrarily large with respect
to log n.
It just has to be at least log n
just to be able to index stuff.
But w could be really big--
much bigger than log n.
For example, w equals
n is not a crazy idea.
If I have a machine that
can represent n numbers,
why not represent n numbers,
each of which is n bits long?
Maybe it takes a little more
time to compute on those--
might want to scale
your running times.
But it's quite reasonable to
think about n bit numbers.
And then this is like
n times 2 to the n,
so this would actually
be exponential time.
If w is 2 to the n, n times t
is exponential in the problem
size, which is n plus 1.
And that's just an example.
w could be bigger.
So this is not what we call
a polynomial algorithm,
or strongly polynomial algorithm
but it's still pretty good,
right?
As long as we know that capital
T is not ginormous, then
this is a great algorithm.
And we capture that
notion with a concept
called pseudopolynomial.
It's not the best term, but
it's the established term.
It's like polynomial,
but not quite.
And the definition
of this term--
so we have definition of
strong polynomial time.
Now, pseudopolynomial time--
I guess I'll write
time here, though you
can measure other things
with pseudopolynomial--
is that we're polynomial in the
input size, just like before,
and the input numbers--
input integers.
OK, so in this problem,
the input integers
are capital T and a0,
a1, up to n minus 1.
So what we want now
is a polynomial,
or what some people
call a multinomial,
where our variables are
all of these integers,
and we want to be
polynomial in them.
So we're allowed to take some
constant power of capital T
and some constant
number of the AIs.
We can't just take the
product of all of them.
That would be big.
So it's a--
I guess I should say
constant degree polynomial.
And indeed, this a--
you might call it
a quadratic polynomial
in the input size
and the-- and one
of the numbers.
So this running time is
pseudopoly, but not poly.
And so while normally, we
think of polynomial time
as good, exponential
time is bad,
pseudopolynomial is what we
normally call pretty good,
to be informal.
Yeah.
So in particular,
pseudopolynomial
implies polynomial
in the special case
if the input integers are
all, at most, polynomial
in the input size.
This should sound familiar.
This is a constraint
we've seen before.
This is the condition when
radix sort runs in linear time.
Radix sort runs in linear time
exactly when all the input
integers are polynomial
bounded in n,
which is the size of the
array, which is the input size.
So same condition
is appearing again,
so this is sort of a fundamental
setting to think about.
And let's see.
So in particular, other
structures we've seen,
like counting sort and
direct access arrays,
are also pseudopolynomial.
Any others?
AUDIENCE: Fibonacci--
ERIK DEMAINE: Fibonacci--
AUDIENCE: Radix?
ERIK DEMAINE: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: Radix--
ERIK DEMAINE: Radix sort--
yes-- technically,
also radix sort--
are all-- they're not
strongly polynomial,
but they are pseudopolynomial.
We thought about this is
a dependence on u, which
we got rid of using hashing.
But if you just use the
order u running time for,
say, build, that--
U is bound on the
input integers,
and that's only good
when this is polynomial.
In general, it's
pseudopolynomial.
Same with counting
sort-- we had an order u.
Now, we improved
this in radix sort
to this running time that
was n times log base n of u--
plus n, if you
want to be careful.
So-- or put a ceiling.
Now, this is a running time
that's a little bit better.
And this is usually called
weakly polynomial-- don't want
to spend much time on this.
But weakly polynomial is
just like pseudopolynomial,
but instead of being polynomial
in the input size and the input
integers, you're polynomial
in the log of the integers.
So this is better.
And it's almost as
good as polynomial--
as strongly polynomial.
We won't really use this notion.
The only place it appears in
this class is in radix sort,
but future classes--
you might care about--
so the nesting is
the best thing you
can be is strongly polynomial.
We just call this
polynomial in this class.
Then we have weakly polynomial,
which is almost as good,
but you have this logarithmic
dependence on the numbers.
And then the next level
is pseudopolynomial.
This is not as good here.
This really only works well
if the numbers are small.
Logarithmic dependence
is pretty good,
because even if
they're exponential,
this is polynomial.
Sounds funny, but log of an
exponential is polynomial--
all right, enough
about pseudopoly.
The last thing I
want to talk about
is reflecting on all of
the dynamic programs we've
seen so far, and
characterizing them
according to the big techniques
that we used in SRTBOT.
The first big technique was, how
do we define our subproblems?
Did we take prefixes,
and suffixes,
or substrings of a sequence?
Did we have multiple
sequences and have
to take products
of those spaces?
Did we have integers and
have to take smaller versions
of those integers?
Sometimes that leads to
pseudopolynomial algorithms,
sometimes not.
And sometimes we
also had subproblems
that were defined in
terms of vertices.
This just happened in
shortest path problems,
because that's the only setting
where we saw DP over graphs.
So let me characterize all the
DPs we've seen in lecture--
not the recitation
ones for now--
in red.
So for example, with the bowling
problem, with bowling pins,
we only had to deal with
prefixes or suffixes, because--
we could just think about what
happened for the first couple
of pins, for example.
Also, for LCS, we had to
take two different sequences,
but then we just guessed
what happened at the--
with the first two
items of each sequence.
And so that only left
us with suffixes.
With longest
increasing subsequence,
again, we just guessed
whether the first--
or maybe we assumed that the
first item was in the longest
increasing subsequence,
and then we
tried to guess what
the next item was.
But that, again, eliminated
everything in between,
so we were just left
with the suffix.
This leads me to
another characterization
of the dynamic programming
techniques, which is for--
in addition to these
basic subproblems,
we often added
constraints and expansion.
And LIS an example of what we
call non-expansive constraint,
where we just added a constraint
to the problem, which was I
want this first item to be in my
longest increasing subsequence.
But that didn't actually change
the number of subproblems,
so it didn't expand the
number of subproblems.
This is, I think,
the only example
we saw with this feature.
Most of the other times,
when we added a constraint,
we also increased the
number of subproblems,
which we'll get to.
OK, also, in a
certain sense, there's
multiple ways to
think about this.
One Floyd Warshall
is a problem--
or we define subproblems based
on prefixes of the vertices.
We had vertices 1
through n, and we said,
is there a shortest path
using vertices just 1 to i?
So that's a prefix of the vertex
set in a particular order.
So you can think of
Floyd Warshall as being--
as involving a prefix.
You can also think of it as
you're given an integer i,
and you're only allowed
to use vertices less than
or equal to i, and so it's also
kind of an integer subproblem.
I will leave it up there.
Also, the two examples
we saw today--
rod cutting kind of--
you could think of it as
either a prefix on the values,
or I would prefer to think
of it down here, where
we had an integer and
we were considering
smaller integers also.
But subset sum
definitely had a suffix,
in addition to having
an integer subproblem.
So rod cutting you
can put down here,
because we looked at smaller
integers-- or up here.
But subset sum really is
up here and down here,
because we both
looked at suffixes
and smaller values of T. OK.
Fibonacci also fits down here.
Fibonacci was another case
where we had a number n,
and we looked at
integer smaller than n.
Good-- I think I've done these.
Now, what problems
involve substrings?
We saw two of them.
One was the alternate
in coin game,
because we were taking
from left or right,
and so we had to look at
substrings in between.
And the other is
parenthesization,
where we had to get
something in the middle,
and that left the prefix
before it and the suffix after.
Both of those are
typical ways where
you get substring problems.
OK, so pseudopoly-- both
of these are pseudopoly,
and those are the
ones that we've
seen that are dynamic
program pseudopoly.
And then, with vertices, it's
all the shortest path problems,
where we also had a parameter,
which is the vertex.
These are natural, because the
goal of single shortest paths
is distance to each vertex,
and so naturally, we
had a subproblem
for each vertex--
for DAG shortest
paths, for Bellman-Ford
and for Floyd Warshall.
OK, back to
subproblem expansion--
we saw a couple of examples--
alternating coin game
and parenthesization--
sorry-- not parenthesization--
yeah, parenthesization--
sorry--
arithmetic parenthesization.
So here we considered
two different versions
of each subproblem--
one where I go first
and one where you go first.
And that was really handy,
though not necessary.
For parenthesization,
it turned out
we needed both min and
max in order to solve max.
So we really only
cared about max,
so we doubled the
number of subproblems
to make it solvable.
For piano and
guitar fingering, we
increase the number of
subproblems by a constant,
or f--
or some f to the f, or some--
for 5 fingers, this is
a reasonable constant--
for some amount of
state that we wanted
to keep track of of the past.
And one example where we
had linear expansion sort of
is Bellman-Ford.
So here we were
expanding by how many
edges are in the shortest path.
So we really only cared
about finding shortest paths.
We said, oh, what
about at most i edges?
So you can think of that
as adding a constraint.
And then there's n
different variations
of these subproblems,
which leads to expansion.
You can also think
of it is just adding
a single constraint, which is I
care about the number of edges.
And that input is an
integer, and then we're
looking at the
natural sub problem
for integers, which is we
care about up to the length
n minus 1.
And now let's consider all
lengths smaller than n minus 1.
And finally, the other
main feature we had
is, in the recurrence relation
and all these shortest path
DAGs, how many incoming
edges did we have?
How many different
branches did we
have to consider, and
then combine in some way?
So we saw a lot of examples
with constant branching--
Fibonacci, where we just--
it's the obvious two-way
branching; bowling,
where we had a couple of
choices at the beginning; LCS,
longest common subsequence,
where we had a couple
of choices what to
do at the beginning;
alternating coin game--
similarly, do we take from
the left or the right--
so just two choices.
Floyd Warshall,
there's two choices.
Do we use that vertex or not?
Subset sum-- do we include
this item in the subset or not?
So that was all
constant branching.
In a lot of the
graph problems, we
got order degree
branching, which
leads to an order e term
in the final running time--
namely, DAG shortest
paths and Bellman-Ford.
And then a lot of examples
had linear branching--
in particular, longest
increasing subsequence,
where we didn't know what
the next increasing item was,
so there are N possible
choices for it.
Parenthesization, where
we had to choose anybody
in the middle as
the last operator--
and rod cutting
that we saw today--
the first rod we cut
could be any length.
And then finally, once
you've considered--
recursed on all
these subproblems,
you have to combine
them somehow.
And in a lot of the
problems, we actually just
take one-- the one best choice,
and that is our final solution.
And in those problems,
the final solution
ends up being finding some
kind of shortest path in a DAG.
But there are a few cases
where we actually took
multiple solutions and
combined them together
to get the overall solution.
And this includes Fibonacci,
which is we added them--
not too interesting.
Floyd Warshall, we
concatenated two paths.
And parenthesization is
maybe the most interesting,
where we had to take two parts--
the prefix and the suffix--
how to solve them and then
multiply or add them together.
And so these problems are not
well-represented by shortest
path in a DAG--
still a DAG involved,
but it's like a
multi-path thing.
And then finally, the
original problem--
often it's just a
single subproblem
is the original problem.
And there are a few examples--
namely, DAG shortest paths,
and longest increasing
subsequence, and Bellman-Ford,
and Floyd Warshall, these
were the order that we covered
them--
so the three shortest paths,
and then longest increasing
subsequence, where here,
because we added this condition,
we had to try all the possible
choices for this condition.
Did we also have one here today?
No.
OK, so in fact, in
retrospect-- or we
know this from the beginning,
but for you, in retrospect,
these four DP lectures
were all about showing you
these mean techniques
of dynamic programming,
from how to set up
simple subproblems
to different types of basic
subproblems to constraining
or expanding those
subproblems, and having
initially very simple
branching, and then getting
to bigger branching and
different kinds of combination.
We wanted to show you all
these ideas in some order.
And if you look
back at the sequence
that we covered
problems, we're slowly
adding these different
main techniques to DP,
and that's why we chose
the examples we did.
There are, of course, many more
examples of DP-- very powerful
technique.
But that's the end.