[SQUEAKING]
[RUSTLING]
[CLICKING]
ERIK DEMAINE: All right,
let's get started.
Welcome back to 006.
Today we are doing some of
the coolest data structures
we will see in this class--
maybe some of the coolest data
structures ever.
Binary trees.
You've certainly seen trees
in many forms in the past,
including in this
class, we've talked--
used trees as a
lower-bound tool for--
in the decision tree model.
But this lecture
and the next lecture
we're going to build
one data structure that
is almost superior to
all data structures
we have seen and can do
almost anything really fast.
First, recall all
the data structures
we've seen so far. arrays,
linked lists, dynamic arrays,
sorted arrays, hash tables.
And the two sets of operations
we're interested in supporting,
the two interfaces,
one was sequences
where we're maintaining
items in a specified order.
We want to be able to insert an
item right after another item
or delete an item in
the middle of the list,
and always be able to
access the i-th item.
We haven't seen any good data
structures for that problem.
We're really good at
inserting and deleting
at the beginning or the
end of the sequence,
but we haven't seen
anything that's
efficient at inserting
in the middle of the list
or deleting in the
middle of the list.
Linked lists, you can't
even get to the middle
in less than linear time.
Array, you can
get to the middle,
but if you make any
changes, you have
to do the shift, which
is very expensive.
So today-- or sorry, next
lecture, for the first time
we will see all of those
operations efficient.
I mentioned our goal where
efficient means logarithmic.
So we're not quite as
good as linked lists
and dynamic arrays at inserting
and deleting at the end.
Those-- there that we
achieve constant or constant
amortized time.
But up to this log
factor, we're going
to get the best of
all worlds where
we can solve all the things, all
the operations that don't build
or iterate through the entire
structure, and that, of course,
takes linear time.
But we can do all the
others in logarithmic time.
For sets, sets we're
maintaining a bunch
of items which
have intrinsic keys
and we want to search by key.
So hash tables are
great if you're only
doing exact searches.
If you want to find a key and
get yes or no, is it in there?
If it's in there,
give me the item.
That's what Python
dictionaries do.
And they're great at
inserting and deleting,
but they're really bad at
find previous and find next.
This is the unsuccessful case.
So if I search for a key and
it's not in my structure,
I would like to know more
than just the answer no.
I'd like to know what the
previous and next items that
are actually in the structure.
So what are my nearest
matches when I search by key?
That's a natural query, and
the only data structure we have
that's good at it
is a sorted array,
because binary search
gives this to us.
If we search for a key bi binary
search and we don't find it,
the position that
we end up at is
right between the
previous and next one.
But of course, sorted
arrays are terrible
for dynamic operations.
We don't know how to maintain--
we can't maintain a sorted
array without any gaps
when we're doing
insertions and deletions.
In some sense, today
and next class,
binary trees let us represent
a sorted order or a general
and order of items
dynamically and still allow
us to do very fast
things like get_at of i
and find previous of the key.
So that's our goal.
We're not going to quite
get to this goal today.
We're going to get an
incomparable thing called
the height of the tree,
and then on Thursday we'll
be able to finish and
achieve this goal.
Today is just in
service to that goal.
So what is a binary tree?
Let me draw an example and
then define it more precisely.
Mathematicians will call
this a rooted binary tree,
in case you've seen
that in 042, say.
Here is a picture.
So this is an example
of a binary tree.
It has a bunch of nodes which
we're drawing in circles.
It has items in the
nodes which we're--
I'm writing as letters here.
So this is item
A, item B, item C.
And it has these
links between them.
This is like linked lists.
But in general,
a node X is going
to have a parent pointer,
a left child, left pointer,
and a right child,
right pointer.
And it also has an
item inside of it.
So I'm going to talk about
node.left is a pointer
to the left--
the node down here.
Node.right, node.parent,
node.item gives me--
so if I look at the
node A, its item
is A. So let me draw
for you some examples.
OK, the parent of A is nothing,
so we call A the root 0.
There's going to be a unique
node that has no parent.
It's sad to have no
parents, but here you go.
Then we have node B
which-- whose parent
is A. Node C whose parent--
its parent is A; node D,
its parent is B; node E,
its parent is B; and node F,
its parent is D. The
alphabetical order here happens
to be ordered by parent.
Then we have left pointer, so
I'll just do a few of them.
So the left pointer of A is
B. The right pointer of A--
sorry, B the node--
these should all be nodes.
I'm circling for nodes,
I'm just reading the letter
for the item to make
it clear that those
are different things.
The right pointer for A
is C; left pointer for B
is D; right pointer
for B is E; and so on.
So in other words,
each of these lines
is a bidirectional pointer.
In this direction, it's
the parent direction;
in this direction,
it's left in this case.
Because it's bidirectional,
we don't draw the arrows,
we just draw undirected lines.
This is, in general, what
a binary tree looks like.
A key invariant is
that if you take a node
and say go to its left pointer--
left child and then go
to that node's parent,
this should be the same as node.
So that's just
saying these are--
parent is always the inverse
of a left or right operation.
This is also true for right.
OK, and that's a binary tree.
Now, the intuition of
what's going on here
is, you could say we're
inspired by a linked list.
Linked lists had a
very similar structure.
Maybe an item-- or there's a
node, it had an item in it,
and it had a next pointer and
it had a previous pointer.
So in some sense, what
we're-- if it's doubly linked,
we had a previous pointer.
If it was singly linked,
we only had a next pointer.
And if you think about the
limits of linked lists,
especially singly-linked
lists, if you just
have one pointer per node,
you can only build the list.
And so the result is this node
is going to have depth linear.
Depth means how
many pointers do I
have to follow to get here
from the root of the structure?
Which for linked
lists was the head.
If it was doubly linked, OK,
I can have a head and a tail
and I can put
bidirections on here.
But then still, the middle
item has depth linear.
So there's no way to get
there unless in linear time.
With binary trees, because we
use two types of next pointers,
left and right, we
can build a tree.
And we know trees in
general have logarithmic--
can have logarithmic height.
And so it's possible in
a tree to get to any node
starting from the root
and only log n traversals.
So that's the intuition
on what's going on.
Now today, we're going to talk
about the height of a tree.
So let me define a couple
of definitions here.
Subtree height of a node.
So a tree decomposes
into subtrees.
So for example, the subtree
rooted at B or the subtree of B
is this portion of the tree.
So it's that node and all of
the descendants of this node.
So because we have
parents and children,
we can generalize in
the familial tree sense.
We can talk about
ancestors of a node.
So the ancestors of F are
its parent, its grandparent,
great-grandparents and so on.
Together, all of these
are called ancestors.
It doesn't quite correspond
to familial trees
because familial trees
you have two parents.
Here, you only have
a unique parent.
Or the poor root has no parent.
We also talk about--
it's like mixed metaphors--
leaves of the tree.
These are people
with no children.
Parents will complain
about this, but many--
like many of us in this room,
they have no children yet,
so we are called leaves.
You can tell your parent, hey,
I'm just the leaf, you know?
Blowing in the wind.
So this-- ah, it's so
many mixed metaphors,
but we always draw
trees downwards
like the root
structure of a tree.
Yet we call the
ends of the roots
leaves, which is upside-down.
Anyway, that's trees for you.
Lots of entertaining analogies.
OK, but ancestors are useful.
Descendants are also useful.
So the descendants of B are
all of its children and all
of its grandchildren
and all the way
down, but just
within the subtree.
So the subtree of X consists
of X and its descendants.
And we think of X being
the root of that subtree.
So we're kind of
forgetting about everything
outside of the subtree when we
talk about the subtree of X.
Let's talk about
the depth of a node.
Depth of a node is--
I guess the number
of its ancestors.
That's right.
I usually think of
it as the number
of edges in the path
from X up to the root.
So every node has a unique
path that goes upwards
until it can't go up anymore.
So the depth of E is 2
because there are two edges--
1, 2-- in the path
from the root A to E.
So maybe I'll read some
depths, depth of these is 2.
Depth of these guys is 1,
depth of the root is 0.
2, 3.
So those are depth.
I'm going to clean
this up a little bit
so we can focus on the image.
All right.
Height-- so depth is
measuring downwards
because if you imagine
depth within water,
this is the surface
of the water,
and then we measure how deep
you are from the surface.
Height is in the
reverse direction.
We're going to measure
from the leaf level
up, because leaves are
the bottom of the tree.
So height of a node is going
to be the number of edges
and the longest
downward path, which
is the same thing as the maximum
depth of a node in X's subtree.
Let's do height in red.
So, how long is the longest
path from F to a leaf?
Well, F is leaf, so all
leaves have depth 0.
Sorry, height 0.
Don't get it backwards.
D here, it's-- so there
are two ways to go down.
This doesn't go to a leaf.
This one goes to leaf
and its height is 0.
So this height is 1.
There's one edge to a leaf here.
B has two leaves it can get to.
We take the longest
one, so that's length 2.
A similarly has height 3.
OK.
So height we measure upward,
depth we measure downward.
One thing we care about
is just the height
of the overall tree, which
is the height of the root.
And I call that h because
we're going to use it a lot.
And what we're going to achieve
today is all of these running
times, instead of being log n,
they're going to be order h.
Today, our goal is to get all
the operations we care about
in order h time.
And then next
lecture we're going
to guarantee that
as always log n
and then we'll get log n time.
So we need to do a bunch
of work to achieve log n.
Today we'll do the work that's
all the tree manipulation.
And as long as your tree
is nice and shallow,
it doesn't have high height,
because logarithmic height,
everything will be log n.
Of course, there are
trees that are really bad.
We can have a tree like
this, which is basically
a linked list where we only
use right pointers and all
the left pointers are none.
So there are trees that are
very high, have high height.
We want to avoid these, but
we won't worry about that
till next lecture.
Question?
AUDIENCE: A couple of questions.
Is the height of C--
of node C is 0 or--
ERIK DEMAINE: What is
the height of node C?
Height of node C is 0.
Because the length
of the longest path--
the number of edges in the
longest downward path is 0.
AUDIENCE: Oh.
ERIK DEMAINE: Yeah.
We're counting
edges, not vertices.
Yeah.
So the height of the tree is,
of course, just the depth--
the maximum depth.
I think that's right.
So the height here is
3, and the maximum depth
is this terribly drawn 3.
So these happen to correspond
in the maximum case.
But We use height to
always mean maximum,
and so that's why we talk
about the height of the tree.
Depth of the tree is not
defined, just depth of nodes.
OK.
How do we use these
trees to represent
either a sequence or a set?
I claim that there
is a natural order
in trees called the traversal
order of nodes or items
in the tree.
So I'm going to define
a particular order, say,
in this example.
Let's do the example first.
The traversal order is going
to be F, D, B, E, A, C.
I feel like I'm in music class.
This is my guitar or something,
but it's not, I hope.
If it is, it's coincidence.
So what is this order?
What I'd like to
do is recursively
define an order where
the root of the tree
is somewhere in the middle, and
everything in the left subtree
is left earlier in the
order than the root,
and everything in the
right subtree is later.
So you can see here
C comes after A,
and then all the other
nodes come before A.
And recursively, if I look at
a node B, this node B, which
appears over here, E
is to the right of it,
but this is all to the left
of A. So E is between B
and A. With B on
the left, and then
F and D to the left of that.
And again, F comes
before D because F
is in the left subtree of
D. So we say for every node,
the nodes in X.left are before
X and the nodes in X.right
come after X.
And this uniquely defines an
order called a traversal order.
That's also called
in-order traversal order.
It's called in-order because
it's in the traversal order,
so it's very
circular, but you may
have seen in-order traversal,
this is the same thing.
There's a very simple
algorithm for computing this.
If I want to iterate--
let's call this-- yeah.
If I want to iterate all the
nodes within a subtree X,
rooted by X, I
just iterate on all
of the notes in the left
subtree, then I output X
itself, then I iterate on all
the nodes in the right subtree.
OK, you may have seen
that algorithm before.
This is just another way
to codify the same thing.
The result is, all the
nodes within a subtree
appear continuously with
no interruptions, and then
the parent--
parents are going to come
before or after depending
on whether this is a
left or a right child.
OK, so now it's just a matter
of connecting the dots,
because we're
representing an order.
And for a sequence, that is
going to be the sequence order.
If we want to store n
items X0 through X1,
we're going to build
some kind of tree.
We're going to put X0 here,
X1 here, X2 here, X3 here, X4
here, X5 in here.
You can see, I'm very used to
dealing with traversal orders.
It takes a little while.
You could also see it here.
We're going to put
X1 on this node, X2--
sorry.
X0 here, X1 here,
X2 here, and so on.
That's the same
order that I gave.
OK, that's four sequences.
For sets, that order is just
going to be disordered order,
and we're going to be
effectively representing
the sorted order of
keys, say, increasing.
But before we get to that, let's
talk about different operations
we can do just playing
around with traversal order.
And then we're going to use
these to build the sequence
and set operations
that we care about.
So a first operation
I'll call subtree first.
Seems appropriate that
it's called first.
It's the first one.
So, given a node,
which I'll call node,
this defines a subtree,
which usually we
draw subtrees as triangles
hanging off of the node.
So here, I would write
X, and then there's
some subtree of all
the descendants of X.
So with subtree
first, I would like
to say among all the nodes in
this subtree, which comes first
in this traversal order?
So just restricting to that
subtree, subtree of node.
So, where is it in this tree?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: A node can be only
part of one subtree, right?
ERIK DEMAINE: A node is
actually part of many subtrees,
good question.
F, F is in its
own-- in the subtree
of F. F is also in the subtree
of D, F is in the subtree of B
like I drew, F as
in the subtree of A.
It's in the subtree of
exactly its ancestors.
But in this operation, when we--
our node only
defines one subtree.
It is the root of
only one subtree.
And that's the subtree
we're talking about.
And then I want to know,
among all those nodes, which
includes the node
itself and other things,
which one comes first
in this traversal order?
This is like practice
with traversal orders.
So where should I
look for this node?
Yeah.
The leftmost leaf, yeah.
And the picture, it's here,
but pictures can be deceiving.
We just want to go left
as much as possible.
When I say go left, I
mean this iteration node
equals node.left.
If you just look
at our definition,
all the nodes in the left come
before X and all the nodes
in the right.
So it's got to be on the
left subtree if there is one.
Of course, we can't
do this forever.
So say until we would
fall off the tree, which
means node is none.
OK, we stop before
that would happen.
So this is like the
directions like, oh, you
keep driving until
you see the store,
and it's the block
right before that.
It's like, well, that's
not very helpful.
So you keep iterating
node equals node.left
until node becomes none,
and then you undo one step.
You all know how to program
that, it's not hard.
So that last non-non-node, which
might actually be the root,
it might be node, maybe
it has no left children.
But in that case I
claim node is the very
first in its subtree
traversal order
because if there are no
nodes in the left that
come before X, then
x is actually first.
So that's it.
Return node.
So I'm modifying
node in place here.
And the very last one before I
hit none, that's the minimum.
That's the first item
in the traversal order.
Similarly, you can
define subtree last.
OK, let's do a more
interesting one.
Successor node.
So in this case, I
want to know what
is the next after none in the
overall tree's traversal order?
Here, I was restricting
to a single subtree.
Now I'm thinking
about the entire tree
and the entire traversal order.
And given a node, I want to
know which one comes next?
Call this the successor.
I feel like I should make some
kind of royal family joke now,
but I don't know how.
So every node has
a unique successor.
Let's do-- let's
do some examples.
So we can start with F--
the successor of
F. If we just index
into this list, the
successor is D. Successor
D is B. The successor B is
E. It's very easy to read
successors off when I have the
traversal order written down,
but let's think about
how to do it in the tree.
Let's see.
There are going to be two cases.
If we look at the successor
of A, it has a right child.
And in this case, the right
child of A is the successor,
but that's not always the case.
I don't have an example,
but if I had another node,
here let's call it
G, the successor of A
is actually G. Because
all of these items
come after A in the order.
But which one comes first?
The leftmost leaf.
That's the problem
we just solved.
So if A has a right
child, what we want
is the leftmost leaf, the
first thing in that subtree.
The right subtree.
Right child subtree.
So this is case 1.
If node.right-- so if we have
a child, then what we want
is subtree first
of the right child.
OK, great.
We can reduce to
this other operation.
But what if the node
doesn't have a right child?
For example, it could be a leaf.
Say we're taking the successor--
I mean, it doesn't
have to be leaf.
It could be F, which
has no children.
It could be D, which has one
child, but no right child.
So what's the successor of F?
Well, it's D, which in
this case is the parent,
but it's not always.
For example, if we
do a successor of E,
its parent is actually
earlier in the order
because E was a right child.
Here, F was a left child,
and so its parent was after.
The successor of
D happens to be B
because it was the left
child if its parent.
OK, so that seems
like the easy case.
If we're the left
child of our parent,
then our successor is our parent
basing on this small example,
but we can argue
generally in a moment.
What's the successor of E?
Well, it's not B because
that comes earlier.
In fact, all the
things in B subtree
come earlier or equal to E.
So we have to keep going up.
And then it turns out
the successor of E
is A because this subtree
was the left child of A,
because B was a left child
of A. So the general strategy
is walk up the
tree until we go up
traversal whose reverse
direction would be left.
So walk up the tree.
When I say walk up, I mean node
equals node.parent iteration
Until we go up a left branch.
So this would mean that node--
before we do the change node
equals node.parent.left.
So we can check that.
And then after we
do that traversal,
that parent is exactly the
node we're looking for.
Why is this true in general?
Let me draw a more
generic picture.
So we're starting at some node.
And let's say its
parent is to the right--
so it comes later in
the order for a while.
Sorry.
I get this backwards,
we're doing successor.
It goes to the left for a while.
So these are-- all these nodes
will come earlier in the order,
because by the definition,
everything in the right subtree
comes after.
And at some point we have a
parent that's to the right,
meaning this node was the
left child of this parent.
And that node, by
definition, will come
after all of the nodes in here.
And could there be anything in
between node and this parent,
grandparent, ancestor?
Only if there was
something in this subtree.
And we're in the case here
where there is no right subtree
of our original node.
So this is where all the
nodes in between node and here
would be.
But there aren't any,
and therefore, this
is the successor.
So that's sort of a general
argument why this works.
I see a question, yeah?
AUDIENCE: So when you
say go up a left branch,
does that mean that
you mark the root node
subtree that is left child into
the traversal order children?
ERIK DEMAINE: Placed
into the traversal order.
So the traversal order is
never explicitly computed.
What we're-- it's
always implicit.
We can't afford to maintain
this as, say, an array.
This is just in our heads.
Maybe I will draw it
with a cloud around it.
We're just thinking this.
It's not in the
computer explicitly.
And the computer
always stores this.
And the reason is,
this is expensive,
we don't-- we can't maintain
an array of things and be able
to insert in the middle,
whereas this is cheap.
I can afford to
maintain this structure
and do all these things.
And so the reason we're
talking about these operations
is they're letting us
manipulate the order--
or in this case, letting us
iterate through the order.
So this was an
algorithm for iterating
through the entire order,
but that takes linear time.
This was getting
started in the order,
finding the first
thing in the order,
and this was given one
node, finding the next one.
How long did these
operations take?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So for the first node,
[INAUDIBLE] to get to that last
node--
ERIK DEMAINE: Right.
At most, the height of
the entire tree-- in fact,
it's going to be the
depth of that first node,
but in the worst case, that's
the height of the entire tree.
In general, all of
these operations
are going to be order h.
We need to think
about it in each case.
Except for this one,
which is order n,
because we're iterating
through the whole thing.
In this case, we're just
calling subtree first,
so that takes order h time.
Here, we're walking up
the tree instead of down,
but that's going to cost
exactly the height of the node.
We happen to stop early,
but worst case, order h.
For all this all the
operations we consider today,
we just want to get
an order h bound,
and later we will bound h.
So the point is, these are fast.
If h is small, like log n,
these are almost instantaneous.
Whereas if I had to update the
explicit traversal order, say,
as an array, I would have to
spend linear time every time
I make a change.
And yes, it would be
fast to do successor
if I had this stored
explicitly, but maintaining
it would be impossible,
maintaining efficiently
would be impossible.
Question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ERIK DEMAINE: Yes.
OK.
Cool.
So these were queries
where I want to follow--
see what's next in the
traversal sequence.
Now let's talk about
actually changing
the traversal sequence.
So these are insert
and delete operations.
These will correspond roughly
to insert at or delete at,
but they're not quite--
we're not quite in the
sequence world yet.
Instead, we're going to
focus on inserting or leading
in the middle of a subtree.
So I'm going to have two nodes.
So in the traversal
order, so node
already exists in the tree.
New is a new node that does
not yet exist in the tree,
hence I call it new.
And what I'd like to do is
insert new right after node.
There's a symmetric operation
which is insert before.
It will be implemented
almost identically.
So we'll just focus on after.
So I want to insert this new
node in the reverse order,
which, again, is in our heads.
This is all in our
thought bubble.
That's what we want to achieve.
And we have to do it by
manipulating this tree,
and however we
change the tree, it
defines a new traversal order.
So maybe let's do
an example first.
Actually, I probably want
this in traversal order To.
Keep track of that.
So, let's say the first
thing we want to do
is insert G before E.
I want to illustrate
both of the operations.
Insert H after E. So
insert G before E.
So conceptually what we
want to do is insert G here.
And the way-- so we're given the
node E and we're given a sort
of empty node--
I mean, a node that
just contains G. It
doesn't have any pointers yet.
And we would like
to put it before E.
Where should I put it?
Left child.
And so that's-- this
is an easy case.
If I'm trying to insert before
and there's no left child,
stick it there.
If I'm trying to insert it after
and there's no right child,
stick it there.
Easy.
So let me write down case 1.
So here, we're inserting after.
So if there's no right
child, put new there.
I'm using informal
language here,
putting this new node
there instead of writing,
for example,
node.right equals new.
Because that's only one
operation you need to do.
One thing you would do is
set node.right equals to new,
but you also have to set
new's parent to be node.right.
So instead of worrying about
those two pointer changes,
because we always do
bidirectional pointer changes,
I'm just going to
use pseudocode,
and then a recitation you'll
see actual Python code
that does all this.
So then there's the other case.
So that should be
the second example.
Insert h after A.
So we already have a node
after A in the right child
in this right subtree.
So where do I want to
put H relative to A?
Well, it should be
to the right of A,
but it should be before C. It
should be to the left of C.
So that would mean we
want to put it here.
In this case, it was pretty easy
because this tree was small.
Where do I want to
put it in general?
Well, wherever subtree
first tells me to put it.
Subtree first is going
to give me the successor.
These are all kind of parallel.
We're in the case now where
our node has a right child.
And then successor tells
us where the successor is.
It is the first node, which
is the leftmost descendant,
in the right
subtree of the node.
A lot of pointers to
follow in that sentence,
but it's clear in the picture.
So in this case we had a node,
and there was no right child,
so we just added new
to be its right child.
In the other case,
we had a right child.
So here is node.
There's this node
here, node.right,
which now we're
supposing exists.
And it defines a whole subtree.
There's this one,
which is the first node
in the reverse order of
the subtree, also known
as the successor of node.
So I'll call the
successor of node
in the current universal order.
But of course, we'd like to
make new the new successor
of the node.
So where does it go?
Here.
We want to add it as a left
child to the old successor.
So put node as--
so take the successor.
And if you look at the
code for successor,
where in this case, so we
know it we'll just call
subtree first of node.right.
And remember, subtree
first went left as much
as it possibly could.
So what that means is this
successor node is guaranteed
to not have a left child.
Because it was defined by
going right once and then going
left as much as you could.
So there's no more
left, which means
we can make one more left.
We just add new
there and we're done.
Now if you look at
the traversal order,
it will be node, then new,
then the old successor
and the rest of that subtree.
It's kind of cool.
In all cases--
I mean, this was constant time.
Here, we spent constant time
after we called successor.
Successor costs order h
time, so this is order h.
AUDIENCE: It's new or node?
ERIK DEMAINE: Hmm?
AUDIENCE: New or node?
ERIK DEMAINE: New, new.
Thank you.
Put new there.
Clear?
OK, that was insertion.
Let's do deletion.
Get the spec right
and the example.
All of these are going
to have two cases.
So let me-- oh, I didn't update.
So now H is after A. So
it should be like this.
You can check, the new
traversal order of the tree
is exactly that.
Next, I'm going to do
a couple of deletions.
Let's delete F first,
and then we're going to--
wow, this is confusing.
We're going to delete
A. So whereas F,
we're supposing we're given a
pointer to F, this node, well,
it's a leaf.
So if I want to delete
it, I just erase it.
Easy.
Leaves are easy to delete,
there's no work to do.
So what that means
is I'm removing
the pointer from D to F.
We'll just erase that guy.
OK, now here's a trickier one.
Suppose I want to delete
the root of the tree.
This is kind of
the hardest case.
But in general,
it'd be somewhere
in between leaf and root.
So if you want to delete
A, if I just erased it,
then suddenly there are
these pointers to nowhere
and I disconnect the
tree into two parts.
I don't want to do that, I
need to keep my tree connected.
So I'm going to play
this trick, which is--
I forget if I use
successor or predecessor.
Predecessor.
So I'm going to look at A. We
already have to find successor
and thereby predecessor.
So I'm going to look at
the predecessor of A, which
is E. We can check that
here, the one before A
is E. This is in
the left subtree.
Find me the rightmost item.
Keep going right until I can't.
That's E.
So now these guys are
adjacent in the order,
and I'm about to remove
A from the order.
So I can momentarily cheat
and swap their labels.
I'm going to erase A and E
here and put E after A. Why?
Because it moves a
down in the tree.
And if I get to
a leaf, I'm done.
So I'm not quite done
because this is not a leaf.
So again, I look
at A's predecessor,
it's now G. Predecessor,
we hope, is always in the--
farther down in the tree.
And then I swap A with G. I have
preserved the traversal order,
except where A falls, just by
moving A earlier in the order
here.
And now A is a leaf
and I can erase it.
So that's what we're
going to follow.
Now in actuality,
it's a little tricky.
Sometimes we need
to use predecessors,
sometimes we need
to use successor.
So the cases are,
if node is a leaf,
just detach it from the parent.
Easy.
That's sort of our base
case in the recursion.
Otherwise, there are two cases.
If-- so if we're not
a leaf, that means
we have a left child or
a right child or both.
Both is going to
be the easy case,
but in general I have either
there's the left child
or there's a right child.
In either case I'm
going to be happy,
so I don't need a both case.
OK.
So what do I do?
If I have a left child,
that guarantees to me
that the node's predecessor is
inside that left subtree, which
means it's lower in the tree.
If I didn't have a left
child, the predecessor
would actually be
higher in the tree,
and I don't want to go higher.
So if I have a left child, I
know the predecessor is lower,
and so I'm going to swap my
item, the contents of my node
with my predecessor's item.
And then I'm going to
recursively delete predecessor.
And that's the
case that we looked
at in this code--
in this example
because we always
had a left child.
If we have a right
child but no left child,
we just do the reverse, we
swap with our successor's item
and then delete the successor.
In either case we're going down.
And so if we start at
some node like the root,
every time we do this
operation, we're walking down,
and then we're walking
down, and in general we'll
keep walking down,
resuming where we left off,
which means total
amount of time we spend
is proportional to the height
of the tree, the worst case.
Question?
AUDIENCE: Why do you do
[INAUDIBLE] a right child to C,
but it's like [INAUDIBLE]
you never had a right child?
ERIK DEMAINE: Right.
So E didn't used to
have a right child.
So we're changing
identities of nodes
when we do this, because
we didn't actually
move this circle.
The circle stayed in
place, and what we changed
was the item that was
stored in that circle.
So whether you call this node E
or A, it doesn't really matter.
It is just the root node.
So we're going to play a lot
of these tricks of moving
the items around.
So far we hadn't
been doing that.
We've just been creating nodes
and placing them somewhere.
But now in this
delete operation is
the first time
where we're changing
what's stored in the nodes.
But we still can define
the traversal order.
The traversal order of
this tree is D, B, G, E, H,
C, which should be what we
get here if I delete F and A.
AUDIENCE: But what if
we created like a tree--
ERIK DEMAINE: And-- sorry, F.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
like it really
matters to you-- like it
really matters to [INAUDIBLE]
ERIK DEMAINE: Trees will
not preserve connections.
That's just the
name of the game.
We are-- we have to allow this,
otherwise we can't do anything.
That's the short version.
OK.
In the last few
minutes, let me talk
about how we take these
trees and implement a set
or sequence.
I've already alluded to this.
So for a sequence, we just
make the traversal order
equal to the order that
we're trying to represent,
the sequence order.
And if we're trying to sort
a set, items with keys,
we're going to make the
traversal order equal to
ordered by increasing key.
Increasing item key.
In some sense that's
it, but then we
need to think about
how do we implement
all of these operations.
So maybe most enlightening
is, for starters,
is finding a key in a tree.
So this is going to
correspond to binary search.
If I'm searching for a key--
let's say I'm
searching for G's key.
And I know-- this going to
be hard in this example.
Maybe I replace these
all with numbers
so I can think about key values.
So let's say 1, 7,
12, 17, 19, and 23.
This is now in key order if you
think of the traversal order.
The property is that all
the keys in the left subtree
of the root are
less than the root,
and the root is less than all
the keys in the right subtree,
and recursively
all the way down.
This is something called the
Binary Search Tree property,
BST property.
These here, we're calling them
binary tree sets or set binary
trees, but there are also
none in the literature
as binary search trees, a term
you may have heard before.
So this is a
special case of what
we're doing where we're
restoring the keys in order.
And then if I want to
search for a key like 13,
I compare that
key with the root.
I see, oh, it's not equal,
and it's to the left
because it's less than 17.
So 13 is left of here, 13 is
right of 7, 13 is right of 12.
And so I know that this
is where 13 would belong,
but there's no
right child there,
and so I know-- and find
that I just return nothing.
If I was doing find previous,
I would return this node,
because I have tried
to go to the right.
The last time before
I fell off the tree,
I was trying to go to the right,
and therefore, that last node
I had was the previous item.
If I was trying to find
next, what would I do?
I would just take this node
and computed successor,
which we already know
how to do, and that
happens to be the root.
So now I can do these
inexact searches.
When I do find previous and find
next, when I fall off the tree,
I find either the
previous or the next.
And then with
predecessor or successor,
I can find the other one.
So that's how we can do find
and find previous and find next.
To do sequences, we need
a little bit more work.
We'll do that next time.